So today’s דף Daf is זין, Zayin, we are a little bit
into it already,
and although דבי Dovy got us a little bit ahead, maybe I
will just start from the top of the דף Daf just because
it’s to like to pick up the whole momentum because the whole
real דף Daf sort of starts from the beginning. So let’s take
a look from two lines from the top. אמר רבי אבהו, Amar
Rabbi Abahu, says רבי אבהו, Rabbi Abahu, גדול יום גשמים, Gadol yom
geshamim, so the גמרא Gemara is now moving away from talking about
different stages of the rain, יורה ומלקוש, Yoreh u-Malkosh, earlier rain, later
rain, interpreting the פסוק pasuk about when God’s, you know, when you’re
given the rains in their right time. And now we get to
a broader discussion about the power and the religious significance of rain,
which if you think about it is really like if not one
of, if not the major theme, certainly one of the major themes
of this מסכת. Masechet. So let’s take a look. Says רבי אבהו,
Rabbi Abahu, great is the day, great is the day of rain
מתחיית המתים m’techiyat hametim from the resurrection of the dead. תחיית המתים,
Techiyat hametim, the resurrection will only be לצדיקים, l’tzadikim, the resurrection will
only be for the righteous, ואילו גשמים v’ilu geshamim when it rains,
בין לצדיקים בין לרשעים, bein l’tzadikim bein l’reshaim, even the wicked benefit
from it.
ופליגי, U-pligi, you might say for some people’s perspective that might be
worse, why should the wicked benefit? But no, it’s better, it brings
life to all. ופליגי דרב יוסף U-pligi d’Rav Yosef and this argues
on רב יוסף, Rav Yosef, דאמר רב יוסף, d’amar Rav Yosef, מתוך
ששקולה כתחיית המתים, mitokh she-shkulah k’techiyat hametim, because it’s equivalent weight to
the resurrection, קבעוה בתחיית המתים, kavuah b’techiyat hametim, that’s why it’s in
the ברכה bracha of the resurrection. And this is going even further,
this is saying it’s even greater than the resurrection. אמר רב יהודה,
Amar Rav Yehuda, says רב יהודה, Rav Yehuda, גדול יום הגשמים כיום
שניתנה בו תורה, Gadol yom hageshamim k’yom she-nitnah bo Torah, it is
as great as the giving of the תורה, Torah, שנאמר, she-ne’emar, יערוף
כמטר לקחי, ya’arof kamatar likhi, let flow like a rain my my
giving, ואין לקח v’ein lekach and the לקח lekach or the take,
the giving, אלא תורה ela Torah refers to the תורה, Torah, שנאמר,
she-ne’emar, כי לקח טוב נתתי לכם ki lekach tov natati lakhem תורתי
Torati אל תעזובו, al ta’azovu, I have given you a good purchase,
a good taking, do not abandon my תורה. Torah. So it is
like, for my תורה Torah flows like rain, so my God’s תורה
Torah was given at סיני, Sinai, the God’s direct giving of it
was at הר סיני Har Sinai and therefore that is like the
rain. רבא אמר, Rava amar, רבא Rava says, יותר מיום שניתנה בו
תורה, yoter mi-yom she-nitnah bo Torah, it’s even greater than the day
of the giving of the תורה, Torah, שנאמר, she-ne’emar, יערוף כמטר לקחי,
ya’arof kamatar likhi, let my תורה Torah drop like rain, flow like
rain. מי נתלה במי? Mi natleh b’mi? When you say let A
be like B, so which are you making dependent on which? הוי
אומר Hevei omer קטן נתלה בגדול, katan nitleh b’gadol, the smaller one
you’re saying is like the bigger one, right? So like I don’t
know, like you know,
her lips are like roses. So the more powerful image is the
rose, and the other thing you’re comparing to the more powerful image.
So the more powerful image here is the rain and it’s the
תורה, Torah, which its power and its impact is less obvious and
less powerful that you’re using the rain to give, you know, to
give to sort of bring, you know, give it its power and
give it its impact. Now I want to say something about that
because it really does reflect a reality of what’s going on in
these, you know, in this whole גמרא, Gemara, which is in the,
you know, biblical texts, it’s true, something like, you know, the giving
of the תורה Torah and other things, or whatever תורה, Torah, etc.,
are all compared to rain. This will be like rain, let it
flow like rain and so on, which means that the power, the
image, not just the imagery of rain, but sort of the importance
of rain is taken for granted. And therefore if you want to
communicate that something else is like, you know, has similar sort of
weight and significance, you know, you want to compare it to the
thing which everybody understands its meaning of. So this is like rain
and let it flow like rain. Oh, rain is beautiful, it gives
life, it’s nurturing, we get that. Oh, so this is like rain.
You know, when the גמרא Gemara has to reverse it, the need
to reverse it shows almost a reversing of a frame of reference.
Like if I, and it makes sense, like if I wanted to
impress upon you how important rain is, you wouldn’t start with a
real appreciation of how important rain is. You’re not a farmer, you
don’t work out in the fields, you don’t really understand why, you
know, why, you know, on a day-to-day powerful emotional basis about the
sense of the necessity of rain and the meaning that it rains
when you need the rain. So I would have to give you
a metaphor so that you could appreciate. Let’s say you were waiting
for your kid to come home from camp and you were waiting
and waiting and all of a sudden how would you feel? Oh,
well, that’s like when it rains, okay? You need that metaphor because
you don’t live that reality on a day-to-day basis. Somebody else you
might have to say the opposite. When my kid came home from
camp, it was like the rain when it finally came. You know,
so the question is מי נתלה במי? mi natleh b’mi? Really reflects
a lot in terms of your experience and your frame of reference
and which type of model is the more sort of powerful and
emotionally resonant imagery. So I think it’s quite fascinating that the גמרא
Gemara is actually sort of doing that. It’s saying if you want
to appreciate how rain is, look at it’s as important as תורה,
Torah, it’s as important as this, whereas in the פסוקים pesukim it’s
actually used to communicate the reverse message. So really sort of shows
you a shifting of, I think, frames of reference.
Okay, so now we have that the rain is important as the
day of the giving of the תורה, Torah, and it's a greater
or equal importance to the תחיית המתים. Techiyat Hametim. So I take
the תחיית המתים Techiyat Hametim idea I mentioned the other day, a
point that I think I read from Reuben Kimmelman who suggests that
the reason they put
rain in the ברכה Beracha of תחיית המתים, Techiyat Hametim, I mean
this is just his argument, is but it's to give more persuasiveness
to the idea of תחיית המתים. Techiyat Hametim. How am I supposed
to believe in the resurrection of the dead? Well look, you believe
that God brings the rain, right? So God brings the rain, what's
the rain? It comes from heaven, it goes into the dead earth,
things are buried under the earth and then things sprout forth. Well
that's תחיית המתים, Techiyat Hametim, things are buried in the earth and
then they're going to come to life. So in that imagery, right,
we don't take for granted תחיית המתים, Techiyat Hametim, we take for
granted the rain, and I try to sort of give you a
feeling for תחיית המתים Techiyat Hametim by talking about the rain. The
גמרא Gemara again is doing the reverse. Rain is so important it's
as great as תחיית המתים. Techiyat Hametim. I take for a point
of departure that you, you know, take for granted תחיית המתים Techiyat
Hametim and now I'm going to help use that to help you
appreciate how important rain is. So it is quite I think fascinating
how this סוגיא Sugya
reverses the frames of reference and talks about like where the point
of departure is. Okay, so רבא רמי, Rava Rami, רבא Rava shows
a contradiction. כתיב Ketiv יערוף כמטר לקחי Yaarof Kamatar Likchi וכתיב Uketiv
תזל כטל אמרתי. Tizal Katal Imrati.
So one is let it go like rain and the word we're
going to see in a minute יערוף Yaarof like לערוף Laarof like
you do עריפת Arifat of the עגלה ערופה Egla Arufa is like
to break the neck. So it's powerful, it's breaking rain, and תזל
Tizal flow is like כטל Katal dew, it's a soft, it's a
flow, it's pleasant. So which one is it? So אם תלמיד חכם
הגון הוא, Im Talmid Chacham Hagun Hu, if he's an appropriate תלמיד
חכם, Talmid Chacham, so כטל, Ketal, then let the תורה, Torah, you
know, sort of flow a drop on him like
dew. Give him your תורה Torah in a loving way. ואם לאו,
Ve'im Lav, now by the way I also remember תלמיד חכם Talmid
Chacham is a student of the חכם. Chacham. So this is like
if your student, you know, your young תורה Torah student is an
appropriate student, then let the flow תורה Torah be nurturing and drop
on him like dew. ואם לאו, Ve'im Lav, but if
he's not acting appropriately or he's got a little bit of a
character issue, then או שעו כמטר, O she'u kamatar, break him, break
his neck or whatever, break him like powerful rain, which doesn't presumably
isn't meant to be treated literally, but it means like, you know,
maybe the תורה Torah you teach has to be a harsher one
because it has to do something to work and correct his character
as well, and gets back to, you know,
another theme that of course we're going to see, which we've already
seen, is about how this, you know, how this leads to our
sort of responsiveness and how we interpret the meaning of the rain.
Is the rain a סימן קללה, Siman Kelala, is the rain a
סימן ברכה, Siman Beracha, you know, what type of message is coming
from this? Again here in the terms of תורה, Torah, but the
fact the way the תורה Torah you teach reflects the person who's
receiving it. And that's going to have also a parallel of how
we interpret the way that what the religious meaning we bring in
to when the rain and how is the rain coming and so
on, which we've already sort of begun yesterday. תנו רבנן, Tanu Rabbanan,
we learned in a ברייתא. Braita. היה רבי בנאה אומר, Haya Rabbi
Bana'ah Omer, כל העוסק בתורה לשמה. Kol Haosek BaTorah Lishma. Now that
we're discussing תורה, Torah, now we're going to move a little bit
away from the rain metaphor and bring in new types of metaphors
in the discussion of תורה. Torah. So we're going to digress a
little, thank you, to discuss about תורה. Torah. כל העוסק בתורה לשמה
Kol Haosek BaTorah Lishma תורתו נעשית לו סם חיים. Torato Na'aset Lo
Sam Chayim. If you involve yourself in תורה Torah for its right
sake, the תורה Torah will become a, you know, an elixir of
life. שנאמר עץ חיים היא למחזיקים בה. Shene'emar etz chayim hi lamachazikim
bah. It is a tree of life for those that hold fast
to it. ואומר Veomer רפאות תהי לשרך. Rifut Tehi Lesharecha. It'll be
a healing to your flesh. ואומר Veomer כי מוצאי מצא חיים, Ki
Motzai Matza Chayim, because one who finds me finds life. So that's
three פסוקים. Pesukim. וכל העוסק בתורה שלא לשמה, Vechol Haosek BaTorah Shelo
Lishma, if you involve yourself in it for the not right purpose,
נעשית לו סם המות, Na'aset Lo Sam Hamavet, it becomes a poison.
שנאמר Shene'emar יערוף כמטר לקחי, Yaarof Kamatar Likchi, let flow like the
rain my לקח, Lekach, my giving, my תורה. Torah. ואין עריפה אלא
הריגה. Veein Arifa Ela Hariga. עריפה Arifa means to break the neck.
שנאמר Shene'emar וערפו שם את העגלה בנחל. Ve'arafu Sham Et Ha'egla Banachal.
So not here just that it's like a harsh תורה Torah that
you teach, but it actually turns into a poison. Now this is
obviously a challenging גמרא, Gemara, it's not the only time the גמרא
Gemara says this because we know the normal principle of the Rabbis
is מתוך שלא לשמה בא לשמה, Mitoch Shelo Lishma Ba Lishma, from
the not right reason, you know, you do things for ulterior motives,
it leads ultimately to doing them for the right motive. So תוספות
Tosafot has the classic answer to this. If you took a look
at תוספות Tosafot כל העוסק בתורה שלא לשמה, Kol Haosek BaTorah Shelo
Lishma, תוספות Tosafot says וקשיא Vekashya והלא אמרינן Veha Lo Amrinan לעולם
יעסוק אדם בתורה אף על גב דאינה לשמה שמתוך שלא לשמה בא
לשמה. Leolam Yaasok Adam BaTorah Af Al Gav De'eina Lishma Shemitoch Shelo
Lishma Ba Lishma. So the גמרא Gemara realizes that we can't always
be doing it for the ideal reason. Saying that it becomes a
poison... ויש לומר דתרי שלא לשמה הוי, Veyesh Lomar Detrei Shelo Lishma
Havei, there'd be two types of not
right, not ideal motivations. דמאן דאמרינן Deman Deamrinan לעולם יעסוק בתורה אפילו
שלא לשמה. Leolam Yaasok BaTorah Afillu Shelo Lishma. כדי שיקרא רבי או
כדי שיכבדוהו. kedei sheyikarei rabbi o kedei sheyekabduhu. You're doing it for
honor, for self-interest, you know, we all have our own personal selfish
motivations even at things that are supposed to be selfless types of
enterprises.
ומה שאמרינן הכא כל העוסק בתורה שלא לשמה נעשה לו סם מוות,
Umah sheamrinan hacha kol haosek baTorah shelo lishma naaseh lo sam mavet,
it's a poison, היינו משיש לומד לקנטר, hainu mishish lomed lekante, you're
learning it as a way of attacking, of critique, of, you know,
of being antagonistic towards the Torah. You're going to learn this in
order to disprove it, you're going to learn this in order, you
know, to lead people astray. That's where it's סם מוות. sam mavet.
So that's, you know, the classic explanation given. I don't necessarily have
a better one, but that's, you know, acknowledging that issue. I should
also say it's an interesting question of what you mean when you
say סם מוות. sam mavet. Like does the גמרא Gemara mean to
understand this like literally, you know, that, you know, somehow you'll be
punished and you'll die as a result? God will punish you? You
know, or does this mean this like more at a religious level?
The same way when it says, you know, when the תורה Torah
gives light, is that to be treated literally or does that mean
spiritual life? You know, well,
I don't
know, yeah, I don't know if I'd translate
this life, תחיית המתים, techiyat hameitim, but, I mean, in terms of
resurrection as opposed to spiritual life. But anyway, but, you know, I
want to hear also if the sense of מוות mavet also just
means it'll lead to like a spiritual death. You think you're involving
yourself in a religious enterprise, but ultimately that could lead to, you
know, a spiritual death as well, depending on what your motivations are
and how you might be perverting it.
So yeah, I want also to say something here because we've been
talking about the use of metaphors, which is we're now going to
get into a section where it's going to get on a whole
discussion of תורה Torah and using a range of different metaphors for
תורה. Torah. Even though we start, the whole thing is about rain,
rain is like תחיית המתים, techiyat hameitim, rain is like תורה. Torah.
Now we're talking about תורה, Torah, let's talk about תורה, Torah, and
then we're going to bring in a lot of different metaphors for
תורה. Torah. So I think it's also interesting, again, talking like about
a shift of a frame of reference that when תורה Torah now
becomes like the central mode, so, you know, the focus of their
existence from their religious perspective. Number one is to appreciate rain as
opposed to the reverse. To appreciate תורה Torah we use rain, but
to appreciate rain we use the תורה. Torah. Rain isn't as important
as תורה. Torah. But also if you want to talk about תורה,
Torah, then you can't, the גמרא Gemara almost feels like it can't
limit itself to one type of a metaphor, rain. That's not a
powerful enough way of communicating everything we want to communicate about תורה.
Torah. So now we're going to have to, you know, bring on
a whole other like, you know, collection of metaphors to give expression
to all the different things we want to say. So the first
one, while it quotes the rain, has already introduced two things: the
tree of life and it's a poison, or it's an elixir, you
know, and we're going to be introducing a lot more different types
of sort of images and metaphors to give a full expression to
the things we want to say about, about תורה. Torah. You know,
it's sort of, on the other hand, like you wonder, you know,
what is it they say, the Eskimos have like what is it,
I don't know if you say Eskimos anymore. What do you say?
Eskimos are fine. Okay, fine anyway. They have like what is it,
seventy different words for snow, you know, if you really know something,
I'm sure you could use, you know, the imagery of rain to
communicate a lot of nuance, you know, if you really appreciate the
totality of that thing, but the גמרא Gemara is going to be
drawing on other types of imageries and it's already started that, yes.
When this passage is talking about תורה, Torah,
is it speaking about an external text or is it speaking about
the authority of the institution of the חכמים? Chachamim?
When it says like, God says like there's like the day of
giving of the תורה Torah or like when it says if you
learn תורה
לשמה?
Torah
lishma?
When it says תורה Torah would become like poison.
Oh, the תורה Torah will become like poison.
Is it not learning, what, what is that תורה, Torah, is this
תורה Torah that we're discussing
about rabbinic authority?
I didn't think so. What would make you say that?
Because what's surprising here is that you've taken the תורה Torah and
in this last
comment from being the crown and the ultimate comparison and the strongest
source of everything in the world to then understanding that it can
be used and abused
and
it suggests that it's going to rise up against those who seek
to abuse it in some way
and
it is going to be סם מוות. sam mavet. Right, what מוות
mavet which we don't know what that means. So who is
סם מוות? sam mavet? The תורה, Torah, the authoritative interpreters of that
text?
Yeah, I don't know, you know, I mean, I'm not saying that
the rabbis don't often sort of put themselves in the equation in
a lot of places, but I never really gotten a sense that
that was what was going to go on here, you know.
Otherwise it's sort of like the end of Raiders of the Lost
Ark. Yeah, if
you're going to abuse the external spiritual something, so then it will
somehow come after you.
Right, that's not the end, that's the middle of the Raiders of
the Lost Ark. At the end when they bury it in the,
they bury it.
Okay, yeah. Anyway,
yeah, I understood it to just mean the גבורה Gevurah metaphysical power
of God's תורה, Torah, you know? I mean, Torah is very often
personified and I don't I don't think it's you know, obviously it's
Torah as the rabbis understand Torah, it's not reading the Bible like,
you know, a Christian would read a Bible, you know? It's reading
it through a rabbinic lens. But I never understood it was about
rabbinic authority in these texts. Yeah. Wait minute, wait minute, we
just want to
clarify the תוספות Tosafot that you read. Is this this distinction emerge
under the influence of the Crusades during their time?
In other words, you mean about people about about about that's an
interesting point. Maybe. I mean, it is a real problem in the
text, but it is interesting that emphasis of לקנתר. lekanteir.
One point I have on this distinction is authority.
Could be. I mean, it's not like the גמרא Gemara does not
also discuss that people that try to use it to find, you
know, to critique and so on. But that's an interesting point. I
will say that רש"י Rashi says when he says זו לשמה, zu
lishma, כאשר ציווני השם אלוקי ולא כדי להקרא רבי. Kasher tzivani Hashem
Elokai velo kedei lehikarei rebbi.
So Rashi understands that the שלא לשמה shelo lishma is a simple
interest of selfish of selfish self-interest, you know, selfish interest. Yeah, did
you have a question?
I was just going to say, I mean, I don't know if
the rabbis of the גמרא Gemara were necessarily thinking of this way,
right? But if you think about, like, the way that רמב"ם Rambam
thinks of השגחה פרטית, hashgacha pratit, right? That it's not that, you
know, you do a bad thing and God press the the smite
button, but that God's sort of has has built into the world
certain natural consequences. Right? And so and his example is, you know,
that the עוון עבודה זרה avon avodah zarah destroyed the first בית
המקדש. Beit HaMikdash. It wasn't that God, you know, spoke to נבוכדנצר
Nevuchadnezzar and said go, it was that had they spent their time
studying what they were supposed to be studying, like war, then they
would have not lost to the Babylonians instead of studying עבודה זרה.
avodah zarah.
Right, so I think you could be understanding that in a normal
way. Right? There are things that you could take that do good,
you know, if you take them the right way they'll be a
cure, and if you take them the wrong way they'll be a
poison. Okay, let's keep on going. The גמרא Gemara says like this.
אמר רבי אמי ליה לרבי זירא, Amar Rabbi Ami lei le-Rabbi Zeira,
רבי
אמי אמר ליה לרבי זירא, Rabbi Ami amar lei le-Rabbi Zeira, לימי
מר לישני, leimei mar lishnei, let the master come and teach and
like, and teach us some Torah. So אמר ליה, amar lei, so
he said, חלש ליבאי, chalash libai, my heart is weak, I'm feeling
a little bit ill. So ולא יכילנא, velo yachilna, I don't have
the strength to give a שיעור. shiur. So לימר מר מילתא דאגדתא,
leimar mar milta de-aggadta, okay, you can't give a real שיעור, shiur,
teach some אגדתא. aggadta. So אמר
ליה, amar lei, I'll let that one go without comment. אמר ליה,
amar lei, he said to him, הכי אמר רבי יוחנן, hachi amar
Rabbi Yochanan, this is what Rabbi Yochanan said. מאי דכתיב, mai de-chtiv,
what's meant by the verse, כי האדם עץ
השדה? ki ha-adam etz ha-sadeh? Like, that's obviously meant rhetorically, is a
person a tree that you should fight against the tree in the
war? This is about not cutting down the fruit trees when you
lay siege to a city. So, is a person a tree? But
okay, anyway, גופא דמינה לביני. gufa de-mina le-veinei. Anyway, וכי אדם עץ
השדה? ve-chi adam etz ha-sadeh? So it's reading it not rhetorically. Because
a person is a tree. Is a person a tree? אלא משום
דכתיב, ella mishum de-chtiv, the verse says, כי ממנו תאכל ואותו לא
תכרות, ki mimenu tachal ve-oto lo tichrot, you should eat from it
if it's a fruit tree and not cut it down. וכתיב, u-chtiv,
and the other verse says if it's not a fruit-bearing tree, אותו
תשחית וכרת, oto tashchit ve-charat, you should cut it down and destroy
it. הא כיצד? ha keitzad? So how does this translate if we're
reading this as a human being? אם תלמיד חכם הגון הוא, im
talmid chacham hagun hu, if he's an appropriate תלמיד talmid student, right,
that and therefore here it means like he's a fruit-bearing tree, you
know? His learning will bear fruit and maybe it also means he
gives תורה Torah to others. Then ממנו תאכל, mimenu tachal, then you
can benefit from his fruit, then you should you should learn from
him. Of interesting, before we were talking about teaching this תלמיד חכם,
talmid chacham, here talking about like the here talking about learning from
him. Anyway, then you can eat from him, benefit from him. ואותו
לא תכרות, ve-oto lo tichrot, do not cut him off, which almost
goes without saying. תוספות Tosafot says it means that if you want
to go learn from another person, don't like cut your ties with
this person. If he's a good person, even if you're not eating
from him, don't cut him off. ואם לאו, ve-im lav, but if
he's not worthy, אותו תשחית וכרת, oto tashchit ve-charat, you should destroy
him and should completely cut off your relationship with him. Don't learn
from him if he's had inappropriate מידות. middot. Right? So here it's
interesting. On the one hand, right, the תורה, Torah, you should make
it a תורה Torah of the heart to try to correct somebody
of poor מידות, middot, and here it's also the תורה Torah that's
produced is not one that you should benefit from. So clearly תורה
Torah is something that is very much intertwined with character and the
importance of character. Again, though, notice now that we're talking about תורה,
Torah, we're shifting the metaphor, you know, we're staying in the agricultural
world at least for now, but we're shifting it from the rain
to the trees. Okay.
So now the גמרא Gemara says like this.
אמר
רבי חמא Amar Rabbi Chama ברבי חנינא, berebi Chanina, מאי דכתיב, mai
de-chtiv, what's meant by the verse, and now we go from trees
and rain to other things. ברזל בברזל יחד, Barzel be-varzel yachad, iron
against iron together. לומר לך, lomar lecha, to tell you, מה ברזל
זה אחד מחדד את חבירו, ma barzel zeh echad mechaded et chaveiro,
the same way if iron, like you have two knives, one of
them sharpens the other, you rub, you know, metal against itself, like
sharpens one sharpens the other. אף שני af shenei אף שני תלמידי
חכמים מחדדים זה את זה בהלכה. Af shenei talmidei chachamim mechadedim zeh
et zeh behalachah. So two students of the sages sharpen one another
in the learning of הלכה. halachah. It's interesting also why it shifts
from תורה Torah to הלכה. halachah. I don't really have a particular
insight into that. But we are now also shifting to the importance
of חברותא, chavruta, and this is like a theme now that the
גמרא Gemara is going to turn on the importance of challenging, you
know, and rubbing against one another ultimately leads to ourselves sharpening our
own understanding.
It's interesting with אגדתא. Agadata.
Oh, that's interesting. That's interesting, the sharpness you need for הלכה halachah
as opposed to a minute ago you only be able to teach
אגדתא. Agadata. I hadn't thought about that. Maybe you're right, maybe there's
a sharpness you need in the halachic realm. Okay, אמר רבה בר
בר חנה: Amar Rabbah bar bar Chanah: למה נמשלו דברי תורה כאש?
lamah nimshalu divrei Torah ka'esh? Again, what to me is most standout
about all of these is the multiplicity of images that are being
produced about תורה, Torah, starting from the whole focus on rain. Okay,
why is תורה Torah like fire? שנאמר, Shene'emar as the verse says,
הלא כה דברי כאש נאם השם. Halo ko devari ka'esh neum Hashem.
So are my words like fire, says God. לומר לך, Lomar lecha,
to tell you, מה אש אינו דולק יחידי, ma esh eino dolek
yechidi, the same way you can't start a fire with a single
log of wood, אף דברי תורה אין מתקיימים ביחידי, af divrei Torah
ein mitkayemim biyechidi,
or you know won't stand by one log. You need like multiple
logs or multiple pieces of word. So תורה Torah isn't sustained by
an individual. You need a community. והיינו דאמר רבי יוסי ברבי חנינא.
Vehaynu de'amar Rabbi Yose berabi Chanina. That's what Rabbi Yose, so that
presumably isn't necessarily about חברותא. chavruta. That's about a community of scholars.
Okay, but this is also what Rabbi Yose barbi Chanina says. מאי
דכתיב, Mai dichtiv, what's meant by the verse חרב אל הבדים ונואלו?
cherev el habadim venoalu?
A sword against the בדים, badim, we'll see how it translates that,
and they will be foolish. חרב על שונאיהם של תלמידי חכמים, Cherev
al sonei'ehem shel talmidei chachamim, a sword should be against the haters
of the sages of the rabbis, which really means the sages of
the rabbis, but we don't want to say something bad about them,
but in the following circumstances: שעוסקים בד בבד, she'oskim bad bevad, if
they learn singly, alone. So that's אל הבדים. el habadim. If you're
learning by yourself and not בחברותא. bechavruta. So now we're not talking
about community in general, but specifically about חברותא. chavruta. If you're learning
singly and not בחברותא, bechavruta, a sword should be against you.
ולא עוד, Velo od, and not only are they doing something bad,
you know,
אלא שמטפשין, ela shemitapshin, not only are they not getting sharper, they're
getting stupider. Okay, they become stupid. שנאמר ונואלו, Shene'emar venoalu, they'll be
foolish. ולא עוד אלא שחוטאים, Velo od ela shechotim, and it's a
foolishness, it's a sin.
כתיב הכא ונואלו, Ktiv hacha venoalu, to be foolish, וכתיב התם אשר
נואלנו ואשר חטאנו, Uchtiv hatam asher noalnu va'asher chatanu, we be acted
foolishly and we have sinned. אי בעית אימא מהכא, I ba'it eima
mehacha, if you want from here, נואלו שרי צוען והתעו את מצרים.
Noalu sarei Tzoan vehit'u et Mitzrayim. So if acted foolishly the princes
of צוען Tzoan and they have led astray Egypt. So being foolish
in תורה, Torah, particularly in הלכה, halachah, leads to going astray yourself,
leading others astray, leads ultimately to sin. Okay, so the great responsibility
of accuracy and sharpening yourself, pushing yourself, and what that means in
terms of also the sense of community and particularly learning בחברותא. bechavruta.
Okay, so a lot of powerful statements here about תורה Torah as
a source of life, the importance of חברותא, chavruta, the downside of
it if done wrong it's a source of death, the importance of
character, you know, if somebody is ראוי, ra'uy, is not
ראוי. ra'uy. So, but all communicated as I said through a wealth
of different imageries.
Okay, where are we? אמר רב נחמן בר יצחק: Amar Rav Nachman
bar Yitzchak: למה נמשלו דברי תורה כעץ? Lamah nimshalu divrei Torah ke'etz?
Again, notice the way also these things are introduced with למה נמשלו.
lamah nimshalu. The גמרא Gemara is even drawing out the different usage
of imageries. Why is תורה Torah compared to a tree?
שנאמר Shene'emar, עץ חיים היא למחזיקים בה. Etz Chayim Hi Lamachazikim Bah.
It's a tree of life. לומר לך, Lomar lecha, מה עץ קטן
מדליק את הגדול, ma etz katan madlik et hagadol, so we're still
on the same theme although a little nuanced. The same way when
you make a fire, you need like the little twigs in order
to get the big logs to catch on fire,
אף תלמידי חכמים קטנים מחדדים את הגדולים. af talmidei chachamim ktanim mechadedim
et hagedolim. So no longer even in חברותא. chavruta. Now we're talking
about the younger, you
know, the younger students to sharpen the more senior ones.
The same way the small little twigs get the big bonfire, get
the big logs to catch on fire.
והיינו דאמר רבי חנינא: Vehaynu de'amar Rabbi Chanina: הרבה למדתי מרבותי, Harbeh
lamadti merabotai, I've learned much from my masters, ומחברי יותר מרבותי, umechaverai
yoter merabotai, from my colleagues more than my masters, ומתלמידי יותר מכולם,
umitalmidai yoter mikulam, and from my students more than all of them.
Why is it that the sense of the students more than all?
So רש״י Rashi says
תני מחדדין, tani mechadedim, רש״י Rashi עמוד ב׳ amud beis 21 lines
from the bottom, he does ששואלים כל שעה. shesho'alim kol sha'ah. They're
like relentless. They're constantly nudging you because they have all these questions
and they have maybe the, you know, the enthusiasm of youth. You
know, you could also say because they ask like the stupid questions
that if you know that nobody else asks, but those are the
real good questions. You know, sometimes you're too much taken in by
the norms of the discipline that you're a part of that like
you don't ask. Sometimes you're too much taken in by the norms
of the discipline that you are part of that you don't ask
the more fundamental questions that are the ones that really need asking.
Sometimes someone says, "I want to ask a stupid question," like, "Oh
no, this is going to be a hard one." So anyway, but
this is the again, the imagery of fire and of wood, now
no longer an עץ etz of tree, but an עץ etz of
like wood, you know, is again used to the importance of the
dynamism that is in תורה. Torah. And I do want to say
something again about that, you know, again, I don't know, because I'm
not a farmer and I haven't like, you know, don't really have
this full experience of what it means rain and rain when you
need it and the different types of rain, but at least from
my, you know, non-farmer perspective, using some of these other imagery gives
much more dynamism. To say תורה Torah is like rain to me
is a little boring. Water, nurturing, okay. Fire, you know, lighting fires,
little twigs, big logs, sharpening sharpening knives one against another, there's much
more I think a sense of like of, you know, dynamism and
life that's being conveyed this way. So again, it is an interesting
question of which is your primary frame of reference here. Okay, so
now the גמרא Gemara continues the following way.
Back to water. I just mentioned water, now we are circling back
to water, not rain, but water. רבי חנינא בר פפא רמי. Rabbi
Hanina bar Pappa rami. רבי חנינא בר פפא Rabbi Hanina bar Pappa
shows a contradiction. כתיב, Ketiv, one verse says, לקראת
צמא התיו מים, Likrat tzameh hatayu mayim, to greet the thirsty bring
out water.
וכתיב, U-ketiv, another verse says, הוי כל צמא לכו למים, Hoy kol
tzameh lechu la-mayim, come all thirsty come to water. So does thirsty
come to water or do you bring the water to them? אם
תלמיד הגון הוא, Im talmid hagun hu, again, back to an appropriate
student. If he's an appropriate student, לקראת צמא התיו מים, Likrat tzameh
hatayu mayim, bring water to him. You should even go out of
your way to teach תורה Torah to an appropriate student. ואם לאו,
Ve-im lav, and if he's not appropriate, הוי כל צמא לכו למים,
Hoy kol tzameh lechu la-mayim, let him come for the water, let
him maybe show a little, you know, a little motivation or a
little perseverance to really, you know, if he really wants to do
it. Maybe it'll be a good test. Maybe it'll bring out a
stronger part of his character. It is interesting one should note that
here he is still a צמא. tzameh. He's still thirsting for תורה.
Torah. You know, so what's אינו הגון? eino hagun? אינו הגון Eino
hagun doesn't mean like he's like there kicking and screaming. He wants
to be learning תורה. Torah. He is thirsty. But maybe certain students,
you need them to a little bit prove their mettle, you know,
before you start, you know, giving them what you have to teach.
רבי חנינא בר חמא רמי. Rabbi Hanina bar Hama rami. רבי חנינא
בר חמא Rabbi Hanina bar Hama shows a contradiction. כתיב, Ketiv, it
says, יפוצו מעינותיך חוצה, Yafutzu ma’aynotecha chutza, your wellsprings should burst forth
to the outside. Same as פסוק, pasuk, famous פסוק pasuk quoted in
the by the by what's his name, by the בעל שם טוב,
Ba’al Shem Tov, right? Isn't that in the letter the בעל שם
טוב, Ba’al Shem Tov, the אגרת ה..., Iggeret ha-..., anyway, he says
that in his like vision that he had, they said, you know,
when is משיח Mashiach going to come? And he was told משיח
Mashiach isn't going to come עד שיפוצו מעינותיך חוצה, ad she-yafutzu ma’aynotecha
chutza, until your wellsprings like burst forth, until I guess חסידיק Chassidic
teachings spread forth throughout the world. Anyway, so your, so here your
wellsprings will burst forth to the outside. וכתיב, U-ketiv, another verse says,
יהיו לך לבדך. Yihyu lecha levadecha. So again, תורה Torah here is
water, back to תורה Torah being water, right? The well, the wellspring
water. But the other פסוק pasuk says, keep it to yourself. Don't
let it, you know, burst to the outside. So what's the answer?
אם תלמיד הגון הוא, Im talmid hagun hu, so if you're teaching
an appropriate student, יפוצו מעינותיך חוצה, Yafutzu ma’aynotecha chutza, then your well,
you know, your תורה, Torah, your wellsprings can burst to the outside,
you can share with him all of your תורה. Torah. ואם לאו,
Ve-im lav, but if he's not appropriate, יהיו לך לבדך, Yihyu lecha
levadecha, you have to keep some of it to yourself. רש"י Rashi
says specifically we're talking about like the esoteric, you know, מעשה מרכבה,
Ma’aseh Merkavah, מעשה בראשית. Ma’aseh Bereshit. But maybe it also means you
have to be a little bit discerning, you know, again, the similar
type of a concern to like the שלא לשמה. shelo lishmah. תוספות
Tosafot as point a potential misuse, you know, some people hear things
and hear what they want to hear and maybe you have to
be a little bit more careful in exactly what you're sharing and
how you're saying it. אמר רבי חנינא בר אידי, Amar Rabbi Hanina
bar Idi, למה נמשלו דברי תורה למים? Lama nimshalu divrei Torah la-mayim?
Here, why is it explicitly, why is it compared to water? דכתיב,
De-ketiv, הוי כל צמא לכו למים. Hoy kol tzameh lechu la-mayim. לומר
לך, Lomar lecha, to tell you, מה מים מניחים מקום גבוה והולכים
למקום נמוך, ma mayim manichim makom gavo’ah ve-holchim le-makom namuch,
the same way water flows from the high place and finds the
low place, you know, finds out the lowlands, אף דברי תורה אין
מתקיימים אלא במי שדעתו שפלה. af divrei Torah ein mitkaymim ela be-mi
she-da’ato shfela.
So again, going back to this issue of הגון hagun and אינו
הגון, eino hagun, and here being a little bit more explicit about
what's הגון, hagun, somebody who is a low, of a, you know,
of a lowly mind, which means here in a positive way, which
means somebody who's humble. Okay, so the תורה Torah stays with somebody
who is
humble. ואמר רבי אושעיא, Ve-amar Rabbi Oshaya, למה נמשלו דברי תורה לשלושה
משקין הללו? Lama nimshalu divrei Torah le-shlosha mashkin hallalu? Why is תורה
Torah been compared to the following three liquids? במים וביין ובחלב, Be-mayim
u-ve-yayin u-ve-chalav, water, wine, and milk. דכתיב, De-ketiv, water it says, הוי
כל צמא לכו למים. Hoy kol tzameh lechu la-mayim. וכתיב, U-ketiv, and
another verse says, לכו שברו ואכלו, lechu shivru ve-acholu, go and purchase
and eat, לכו שברו בלא כסף ובלא מחיר, lechu shivru belo chesef
u-velo mechir, go purchase without money and without exchange, יין וחלב, yayin
va-chalav,
wine and milk. And that's understood to refer to תורה. Torah. So
why is תורה Torah compared to water, wine, and milk? לומר לך
lomar lach to tell you מה שלושה משקים הללו אין מתקיימים אלא
בפחות שבכלים mah shlosha mashkim halalu ein mitkaymim ela bapachot shebakeilim the
way you keep water, wine and milk fresh is you keep them
not in like fancy gold and silver vessels as we'll see, you
keep them in pottery vessels and that helps keep them fresh. אף
דברי תורה אין מתקיימים אלא במי שדעתו שפלה af divrei Torah ein
mitkaymim ela bemi shedaato shefala similarly Torah is only kept by somebody
who is humble, you know who's not taken by themselves and the
lowliness of the vessel helps contain the Torah within. כדאמר ליה ברתיה
דקיסר לרבי יהושע בן חנניה kedaamar lei bartei dekeisar lerabbi Yehoshua ben
Chananya so the daughter of the Caesar said to Rabbi Yehoshua ben
Hanania אי חכמה מפוארה בכלי מכוער ei chochma mefoara bichli mechoar
what beautiful Torah is being kept in such a disgusting vessel! Apparently
Rabbi Yehoshua ben Hanania was somewhat ugly. שאמר לה so amar lah
so he said to her אביך רמי חמרא במאני דפחרא avich rami
chamra bemanei depachra
does your father keep his wine in pottery vessels? אמרה ליה amra
lei she said to him אלא במאי ela bemai what do you
think we should be putting it in? אמר לה amar lah he
said to her אתון דחשיביתו atun dechashivitu look you guys are so
important, you're the Caesar's household, רמי במאני דדהבא ובכספא rami bemanei dedahava
ubechaspa
why don't you put it in gold and silver vessels?
אזלה so azla she went ואמרה ליה לאבוה veamra lei laavua she
said to her father רמי לכו חמרא במאני דדהבא ובכספא rami lechu
chamra bemanei dedahava ubechaspa well let's put our wine in gold and
silver vessels. Okay, אזלו so azlu they did it ותקיף vetakif and
it turned sour. אתו ואמרו ליה atu veamru lei
so people came
and said to the Caesar what happened. אמר לה so amar lah
so he said לברתיה lebartei he said to his daughter מן אמר
לך הכי man amar lach hachi who told you to do this?
Where'd you get this crazy idea? אמרה ליה amra lei she says
to him
רבי יהושע בן חנניה Rabbi Yehoshua ben Chananya so this Rabbi. קריוה
so karyua they called him. אמר ליה amar lei they said to
him אמאי אמרת לה הכי amai amarta lah hachi why did you
tell this to her? אמר ליה amar lei he said to the
Caesar כי היכי דאמרה לי אמרי לה ki heichi deamra li amri
lah the way that she said to me I said to her.
He said you want to keep something beautiful in an ugly vessel
so I said back to her Rashi says he did not explicitly
tell her like you should put it into this other vessel like
that would be playing with fire in the Caesar's house, but Rashi
says he was responding to her rhetorically and she interpreted it as
a literal suggestion. He said well why don't you put your wine
in gold and silver, oh that's a good idea. So he wasn't
actually suggesting it. Anyway, okay so the Gemara says and the Gemara
actually we talked before about empirical evidence, the Gemara actually does challenge
this empirically. The Gemara says ואיכא שפירי דגמירי veika shapiri degmiri what
do you mean? There are very handsome beautiful people good-looking people that
know Torah. So the Gemara says דף ז עמוד ב daf zayin
amud bet אי הוו סנו טפי הוו גמירי ei havu sanu tfei
havu gmiri you know if they were ugly they would know even
more than they know now. So Tosafot says not necessarily if they
were ugly but if they valued beauty less or society valued beauty
less, not necessarily we want them to be ugly but anyway it's
not you know it still gets in the way. Our own sense
of being a little bit too taken by ourselves doesn't allow us
to be completely dedicated and self-sacrificing and also maybe search for truth
in the same way, maybe we get a little bit too much
focused on our own sense of what's right and not a full
sense of you know of being of the sense of this lowly
vessel that can really sustain and contain everything.
That's a great.
What? Yeah. That or sour grapes. Now okay all right anyway. דבר
אחר davar acher סנו sanu is like משנאי?
mesanai? Yeah.
Yeah, but like I mean like
if they reject that more. They would...
no no no. Well that's I think like Tosafot reads it, but
Rashi just
I think just reads it if they were like if they were
more disgusting like not you know so so yeah. Tosafot says אם
היו שונאים היופי im hayu sonim hayofi okay that's how Tosafot says
right at the process of the previous amud. Okay. Um
okay דבר אחר davar acher מה שלושה משקים הללו אין נפסלים אלא
בהיסח הדעת mah shlosha mashkim halalu ein nifsalim ela behesech hadaat back
to these three liquids now, they only will spoil if you stop
paying attention to them, you don't put you know you don't put
the cover back on and put them in the
fridge. So אף דברי תורה אין משתכחים אלא בהיסח הדעת af divrei
Torah ein mishtakchim ela behesech hadaat Torah will only be forgotten if
you stop paying attention to it which is an interesting way of
phrasing it, you know as opposed to saying like like you know
it'll so easily be forgotten unless you really work at paying attention,
here it's like more like the negative which is a little bit
more reassuring as well. As long as you don't have היסח הדעת
hesech hadaat it won't be forgotten. I don't know to me it's
a little bit more more reassuring than saying you you have to
repeat it you know you have to constantly pay attention or else
or else or else you'll lose it. But anyway,
but that is also very different than the idea of being a
you know a nice vessel or an ugly vessel, here it's אלא
בהיסח הדעת ela behesech hadaat maybe if it's in a nice vessel
that won't cause it to be forgotten, it'll only be forgotten if
you stop if you stop focusing and paying attention to it. אמר
רבי חמא בר חנינא amar Rabbi Chama bar Chanina now so that
was a whole big digression about Torah, you see again sort of
the world that's the bigger frame of reference of the Gemara is
the Torah but now we're circling back to the rain which is
where we started. So we said... The day of rain is like
the day of giving of the תורה Torah, *Torah*, the day of
rain is like the resurrection, and now we're going to get another
thing about the power of the day of rain. אמר רבי חמא
ברבי חנינא *Amar Rebi Chama bar Rebi Chanina* גדול יום הגשמים כיום
שנבראו שמים וארץ *Gadol yom hageshamim kiyom shenivreu shamayim va'aretz*. It's as
great as the day of the creation of the heaven and the
earth, שנאמר Shene’emar, *Shene'emar* הרעיפו שמים ממעל ושחקים יזלו צדק *Har'ifu shamayim
mima'al ushchakim yizlu tzedek*. The heavens will drip forth from above and
the heavens also whatever will flow righteousness. תפתח ארץ tiftach eretz, ויפרו
ישע veyifru yesha, *Tiftach eretz veyifru yesha*. The earth will open up
and salvation will flower
forth. וצדקה תצמיח יחד *U'tzedakah tatzmiach yachad*. Salvation and righteousness will blossom
together. אני ה' בראתיו *Ani Hashem berativ*. I God have created it.
בראתים *Beratim* לא נאמר *lo ne'emar*, it doesn't say created them, אלא
בראתיו *ela berativ*, it. What's the it here? So the גמרא Gemara
*Gemara* understands that the it is the rain, is
what the heavens are dripping forth. So therefore the rain and it
uses the word ברא *bara* to create, so it's like the creation
of the world and of the heaven and the earth. I do
want to also say something about these metaphors about rain and this
is very important to the theme we're dealing with, because the question
is, and this is going to be a major focus, is the
whole importance of the rain because we need the rain in order
to live and therefore we pray because without having the rain we
don't have what's sustaining us? Or that's one way of learning it,
but what we are going to see in this מסכת Masechet. *Masechet*
and I think it's already been alluded to is much more than
that, it's that the presence or absence of rain besides its importance
in our
physical well-being
is a manifestation of God's closeness or distance to us and we've
talked about that. We pray up to God, so the rain comes
down from God, it's about giving life but ultimately it's a manifestation
of God's connection to us. So therefore these ideas, it's like the
day of the resurrection. You could read this as oh because resurrection
is about giving life and rain gives food which is life. It's
like the תורה Torah *Torah*. תורה Torah. *Torah* gives spiritual life, rain
gives physical life. But also all of these things are very much
about God's direct interaction with the world. God creates the world, תחיית
המתים techiyat ha-metim, *Techiyat Hametim* is like this
world-wide obviously miraculous almost re-creation and about the future, and the giving
of the תורה Torah. *Torah* is the direct, is God's revelation. So
all of these things, rain then becomes about God's revealing God's presence
in this world and us experiencing God's presence in this world in
a way that brings life and brings creation and brings all these
things, but it's all very much also about God's very self and
manifest presence. And that certainly seems to be like a common theme
here and something that we're going to be regularly
revisiting.
You're phrasing an understanding of the authors of the גמרא *Gemara* at
a time when their agricultural system was 100% dependent upon the natural
recurrence of rain?
You
mean that it was more than just the that they saw religious
meaning in it and they saw a sense of are we feeling
God, we see the rain, we feel the immediate sense of God
answering our prayers and God desiring us?
That's
what I'm sensing from the גמרא *Gemara*.
I'm questioning whether you're describing what you read as the intention of
the authors of the גמרא *Gemara* or whether you're describing man's interaction
with rain today.
No, not with rain today. I think like I said earlier, I
think with rain today we are first of all, we're very scientific
and we don't see it religiously at all. And number two is
most of us here are completely removed from that reality, so we
don't treat it with that much import.
Even if you were in the reality in developed economies where the
agricultural system is not as dependent on rain in any.
That's also true. Our dependence on rain, right, I mean it depends
where, I mean in ישראל *Yisrael* people are much more sensitive to
that sense of but yes, I completely agree. I'm not at all
suggesting that's our experience. I'm saying that that is I think both
the physical reality of the גמרא *Gemara*, its dependency and the power
of it and their lived lives, and their religious sensibilities
and the lack of I think how they have read everything through
a scientific lens. I mean I also think that's an important point
as well which is even for people that understand that there are
other natural causes to things, I think there's a question of a
primary lens of in which we interpret reality. Like I think for
us it's not just that we understand there are natural causes, we
really interpret everything through a scientific lens, through natural causes as opposed
to a type of a mentality that fundamentally interprets things
religiously even if they could understand that there are also natural explanations
for things.
Is your distinction one between how you analyze this or are you
asserting that that's an error?
I'm not asserting it's an error. I'm talking about different
perspectives, just different ways of interpreting reality. I mean both can be
true but there's a question of what's your primary lens. Alright anyway,
so but yes, I am talking about very much to how I
think the גמרא *Gemara* is. it is experiencing this based on all
of those things. It's religious mentality and it's the way the role
that rain played and their connection to the role that rain played,
and I do think that as we'll see, that consistently is the
theme of this of this מסכת. Masechet So again, not just its
importance because look, it gives life, but because of look, God is
operating in the world and we're experiencing God's operating in the world.
אמר רבי אושיעא, Amar Rabbi Oshaya, says רבי אושיעא, Rabbi Oshaya, גדול
יום גשמים, Gadol yom geshamim, great is the day of rain, שאפילו
ישועה, she’afilu yeshua,
even salvation, פרה ורבה בו, para ve’raba bo,
is fruitful and multiplies on a day of rain. So there again
is a nice expression. Rain is when it's raining, that's also a
sense of divine salvation. שנאמר, shene’emar. as the verse says, תפתח ארץ,
the land will open up, ויפרו ישע, and salvation will will multiply,
will flourish. אמר רבי תנחום בר חנילאי, Amar Rabbi Tanchum bar Chanilai,
אין גשמים יורדים, ein geshamim yordim, the rains do not descend, אלא
אם כן נמחלו
עוונותיהם של ישראל. ela im ken nimchalu avonoteihem shel Yisrael. And now,
so salvation is also intimately connected. If rain is also about God's
presence, you know, and salvation, God's sort of bringing
God's
nurturing to the world and immediate acting in the world, so then
it also connects very much to our sins or our מצוות. mitzvot.
So therefore, if it's raining, it means that our sins have been
forgiven, that God is close to us, God desires us. What's that
closeness about? That our sins are forgiven, שנאמר. shene’emar Now, by the
way, whoever said we sinned? And this also puts an important twist
on the מסכת. Masechet. The מסכת is it's not raining, oh my
God, we have to cry out, maybe we sinned, etc., and we'll
talk about the role that sin plays. But when you say the
day your sins are forgiven, what does that associate with? Sins are
forgiven like, oh, like it's יום כיפור, Yom Kippur, it's a day
of grace, it's a day of... I wasn't even thinking I had
sinned, but the fact that it's raining shows me how much God
desires me, you know? It's a complete expression of divine love and
divine grace.
וישע וישועה. Veyesha ve’yeshua.
Well, maybe also.
There is an implicit possibility.
Right, about the water as purification. Although right, I don't exactly see
that here, but okay. But I do see it as again, as
an expression that how how much God God is close to us
and intimately with us. Yes.
That
the power of our our sins have the power to disrupt the
course of nature.
Right. And that we're going to see in the remainder of the
מסכת. But I'm saying even before that, I mean it's one thing
to say we've sinned, it hasn't rained, we'll do תשובה, teshuva, it'll
rain, that'll show that we fixed our problem. This is like we
didn't even acknowledge that there was a problem. It's raining, that shows
how much God loves us, you know, and the very expression of
rain is an expression about like unconditional love and I've forgiven anything
wrong that you've ever done. רצית ה' ארצך, Ratzita Hashem artzecha, God,
you have desired your land, שבת שבות יעקב, shavta shevut Yaakov, you
have returned the returning of Jacob, נשאת עוון עמך, nasata avon amecha,
you have lifted off the sin of your nation, כסית כל חטאתם
סלה, kisita kol chatatam sela, you have covered over all of their
sins. אמר ליה זעירי מדיהבת לרבינא, Amar lei Ze’iri mi-Dehavat le-Ravina, says
זעירי Ze’iri from יהבת, Dehavat, as Rashi points out it's not the
זעירי Ze’iri סתם stam who lives much earlier, said to רבינא, Ravina,
אתון מהכא מתניתו לה, atun mehacha matnitu lah, you learn out that
idea from that פסוק pasuk you just quoted. אנן מהכא מתנינא לה,
anan mehacha matnina lah, we learn it out from the following פסוק,
pasuk, ואתה תשמע השמים וסלחת לחטאת עמך, ve-atah tish’ma hashamayim ve-salachta le-chatat
amecha, you'll hear the heavens and you will forgive the sin of
your people. Now, that פסוק pasuk is different, because that פסוק pasuk
as we read when we started תענית Taanit from the תפילה tefilla
of שלמה Shlomo is, there's no rain, people will cry out to
you, and you'll forgive them and bring the rain. But that's very
much that process of starting with a sense of sin and the
distance because of sin. Again, I think it gets a different valence
when you just start by saying if it's raining, it means any
sin you've had is forgiven. אמר רבי תנחום בריה דרבי חייא איש
כפר עכו, Amar Rabbi Tanchum breih de-Rabbi Chiya ish Kefar Akko, אין
גשמים נעצרים, ein geshamim ne’etzarim, the rains are only withheld, אלא אם
כן נתחייבו שונאיהם של ישראל כליה. ela im ken nitchayvu soneihem shel
Yisrael kelaya. Now we get to the reverse. If the presence of
rain is God's giving of the תורה, Torah. תחיית המתים, salvation, forgiving
of sin, then the absence of rain is a sense of God's
distancing from us. And therefore, if there's no rain, if they're being
withheld, it's because the Jewish people, or literally the haters of the
Jews, are deserving of destruction.
שונאיהם של ישראל
Soneihem shel Yisrael are Jews. Right, are Jews, right, are deserving of
destruction, שנאמר shene'emar, as the verse says, ציה גם
חום יגזלו מימי שלג שאול חטאו. tziya gam chom yigzelu meimei sheleg
sheol chatau. So the the famine and the heat, they have stolen
the rains of the snow, they have sinned to the very depth.
So אמר ליה זעירי מדיהבת לרבינא, amar lei Ze’iri mi-Dehavat le-Ravina, so
if there's the thirst and the heat, meaning there's no rain, and
the and the rains, the waters of the rain have been taken
away, that's because they deserve to go down to the שאול, sheol,
to the very depths because of their sins. אמר ליה זעירי מדיהבת
לרבינא, Amar lei Ze’iri mi-Dehavat le-Ravina, says זעירי Ze’iri from יהבת Dehavat
said to רבינא, Ravina, אתון
מהכא מתניתו לה, atun mehacha matnitu lah, you learn, dropping by the
minute, אתון מהכא מתניתו לה, atun mehacha matnitu lah, you're learning it
out from here, something I said, you're learning it out from here,
אנן. anan. אנן מהכא מתנינן לה *Anan me-hacha matnisinan leih*. We learn
it up from the following verse: ועצרת השמים *V'atzarta hashamayim*, I will
hold back the heavens, ולא יהיה מטר *v'lo yiheiyeh matar*, ואבדתם מהרה
*va'avadtem meheira*, and you'll be quickly driven from the land. So very
clear, you know, if you sin, no rain, and you're driven from
the land. One does wonder why it did not quote that פסוק
*pasuk* which is in the תורה Torah, *Torah* and much more, first
of all, much easier the פסוק *pasuk* to interpret. But anyway, but
maybe again, maybe that's you know at the collective and or that's
about exile, this is about גיהנום *Gehennom* or destruction. But anyway, not
exactly clear why one would have gone to the earlier verse rather
than this. אמר רב חסדא *Amar Rav Chisda*: אין גשמים נעצרים *ein
geshamim ne'atzarim*, so again focusing now on what absence of rain means,
rains are only withheld אלא בשביל ביטול תרומות ומעשרות *ela bishvil bitul
trumos u'ma'asros*. Now we're getting to more minor sins, you know, and
now we're getting I think to the lesser point about the broader
theological meaning and sort of, you know, how the interpretation of reality
to this type of a sense of this thing happens for this
particular sin, like a type of a correspondence. Okay, שנאמר
*shene'emar* as the verse says: ציה גם חום יגזלו מימי שלג *tziyah
gam chom yigzlu meimei sheleg*. מאי משמע *mai mashma*? What do you
get it from that verse? תנא דבי רבי ישמעאל Tana devei Rabbi
Yishmael, *Tana d'vei Rabbi Yishmael*: בשביל דברים שצויתי אתכם בימות החמה *bishvil
devarim shetzivisi eschem biyemos hachama*. Why is it that you're not getting
the waters of the snow and the rain? Because of חום *chom*,
because of things I have told you. ציה *tziyah* like צוה *tzivah*,
things I've commanded about the summer and the sunny months, the spring
and the summer, which is to give the תרומות ומעשרות *trumos u'ma'asros*
when you're harvesting the grain.
What does ציה *tziyah* itself mean
in the פשט *pshat*?
Thirst, thirst, like צמא *tzamei*.
Yeah. ולא עשיתם *v'lo asisem* and you didn't do them, יגזלו מכם
מימי שלג בימות הגשמים *yigzlu mikem meimei sheleg biyemos hageshamim*. So if
you did not do the things I were צוה *tzivah* in the
days of the sun, then the rains will be stolen from you
in the times of the rain. אמר רבי שמעון בן פזי *Amar
Rabbi Shimon ben Pazi*, now of course there by the way, there
is the logic there is I do think this makes it a
little bit less, a little more mundane, you know, it's a little
bit like equivalence, but the logic you understand. The logic is תרומות
ומעשרות *trumos u'ma'asros* is about giving from the grain that grew as
a result of the agricultural blessing. If you do not acknowledge God
and God's gifts and God's presence and God's hand in your agricultural
bounty, the response will be that you will be punished accordingly and
you will not get blessed in the same way. So there's a
very, you know, logical type of a correspondence
there. Now we get to maybe a little less of a logical
correspondence. אמר רבי שמעון בן פזי *Amar Rabbi Shimon ben Pazi*: אין
גשמים נעצרים אלא בשביל מספרי לשון הרע *ein geshamim ne'atzarim ela bishvil
mesaprei lashon hara*. The rains are withheld because people speak a evil
tongue. שנאמר *shene'emar*: רוח צפון תחולל גשם ופנים נזעמים לשון סתר *ruach
tzafon techolel geshem upanim niz'amim lashon saser*. So the northern wind will
like blow away the rain and like angry face will
like
a speech in hiding or in private, a secret speech. So what
does that mean? It means that the לשון סתר *lashon saser* is
לשון הרע *lashon hara*, gossip which is said in private, and as
a result of that the wind will blow away the rain and
you won't have the rain. אמר *amar* so again I don't exactly
get the correspondence there. אמר רב סלא אמר רב המנונא *Amar Rav
Sala Amar Rav Hamnuna*: אין גשמים what?
Your wind can cause death to another
person?
The power about wind?
Your לשון הרע *lashon hara* can cause,
right, so the power of
extending that out.
Right, so that's the power of the wind. Right, I was thinking
about that, the רוח *ruach* is about but the question about the
power of the rain, you
know, something says the rain in other words gives life,
and your רוח *ruach*, your רוח *ruach* blew away the rain as
it were, a different type of a רוח *ruach*.
Right, bad energy, לשון הרע *lashon hara*, so you're not going to
get the life giver.
Right, right, no that I see. Okay, right, that's true, right. Okay,
but I was thinking like specifically in the context of rain. I
saw you were also speaking about the רוח *ruach*, the wind blows
away the rain. I'm talking about rain. I understand, I understand. Okay.
אמר רב סלא אמר רב המנונא *Amar Rav Sala Amar Rav Hamnuna*:
אין גשמים נעצרים אלא בשביל עזי פנים *ein geshamim ne'atzarim ela bishvil
azei panim*. So rain is withheld because of brazenness. Okay, again don't
exactly get the exact correspondence. שנאמר *shene'emar*: וימנעו רביבים ומלקוש לא היה
ומצח אשה זונה היה לך isha zonah hayah lach, *vayimane'u revivim u'malkosh
lo haya u'metzach isha zona haya lach*. Withheld, you know, the drops
and the rain, and מלקוש *malkosh* there was no rain, and the
forehead of a brazen woman or of a prostitute you had. So
the brazenness is somehow drives away the rain. Again, it's in the
פסוק *pasuk* but I don't get the exact correspondence. ואמר רב סלא
אמר רב המנונא *V'amar Rav Sala Amar Rav Hamnuna*: כל אדם שיש
לו עזות פנים kol adam she'yesh lo azus panim, *kol adam she'yesh
lo azus panim*. Now we're talking about brazenness, any person
who has brazenness סוף נכשל בעבירה *sof nichshal ba'aveirah*. Ultimately it leads
to sin, which usually here and here means sexual sin. שנאמר *shene'emar*:
ומצח אשה זונה היה לך *u'metzach isha zona haya lach*. Right, so
it talks about, you know, sexual sin and somehow connected with the
מצח metzach, *metzach*, with the brazenness. Presumably it means maybe if you're
not ashamed sometimes you know... It's
not it will lead to sin, if you're showing brazenness, that's an
indicator that you have already sinned, particularly sexual sin, שנאמר היה לך,
אשה זונה היה לך, you had a prostitute, ולא נאמר יהיה לך,
velo ne'emar yihyeh lach, you will have a prostitute. So reading מצח,
metzach it's a מצח שנאמר אשה זונה היה לך. shene'emar isha zonah
hayah lach. So that brazenness is coming from a way of maybe
covering over, you know, your the sins that you have done, your
sexual sins. אמר רבה בר אבונה, Amar Rabbah bar Avuna, כל אדם
שיש לו עזות פנים, anybody that has brazenness, מותר לקרותו רשע, mutar
likroso rasha, you can call them evil. So the same way before
we digressed about Torah, now we're digressing about brazenness, שנאמר העז איש
רשע בפניו. shene'emar he'ez ish rasha b'fanav. So like to
be strong against a wicked person in his face, and it calls
them an איש רשע, ish rasha, wicked. So you can call him
wicked. רב נחמן בר יצחק אמר, Rav Nachman bar Yitzchak amar, מותר
לשנאותו, mutar lishnoso, you can hate him, שנאמר ועז פניו ישונא, shene'emar
v'oz panav yeshuneh, the strength of his face will change, אל תקרי
ישונא אלא ישנא, al tikri yeshuneh ella yisaneh, you shall hate him.
אמר רב קטינא. Amar Rav Katina. All right, so that was a
digression
about brazenness.
Is there anything behavioral about when they're מותר לשנאותו? mutar lishnoso? The
גמרא says, you know, מותר לשנאותו. mutar lishnoso. So is it in
your heart and then your mind, or do you stop talking to
them, do you stop sitting with them?
Yeah, it's a good question.
I mean, to one degree, it's referring to the פסוק לא תשנא
את אחיך בלבבך, pasuk lo sisna es achicha bilvavecha, so it's saying
it's מותר לשנאותו, mutar lishnoso, but there actually are some practical implications
for that in various גמרות. Gemaras. So I think it probably means
both, but you're right, it's not being elaborated here. אמר רב קטינא,
Amar Rav Katina, אין גשמים נעצרין אלא בשביל ביטול תורה. ein geshamim
ne'etzarin ella bishvil bitul Torah. So to come full cycle, if and
again, one also wonders if there's an echo here about all this
brazenness about a תלמיד חכם talmid chacham of a good character and
not a good character, but now we're coming full cycle about Torah
and rain. So we never said before that it rains because of
our Torah, but here we're saying that if there's no rain, it
is because of
ביטול תורה, bitul Torah, שנאמר, okay wait, אלא שנאמר, ella shene'emar, it
says
בעצלתים, ba'atzaltayim, with this laziness, like being עצל, atzel, ימך המקרה, yimach
hamikreh, the מקרה mikreh will become weak. So what does this mean?
בשביל עצלות שהיה בישראל, Bishvil atzlus shehayah b'Yisrael, because of the laziness
in Israel, שלא עסקו בתורה, shelo asku baTorah, they did not fully
involve themselves in Torah, נעשה שונאו של הקדוש ברוך הוא. na'asah sono'o
shel Hakadosh Baruch Hu. Before we talked about שונאיהם של תלמידי חכמים
sone'ihem shel talmidei chachamim and שונאיהם של ישראל. sone'ihem shel Yisrael. Here
we're talking about שונאו של הקדוש ברוך הוא, sono'o shel Hakadosh Baruch
Hu, which is a way of saying God, okay, but we don't
want to say something bad about God, but it is as if
God became מך, mach, weak. Our lack of Torah weakened God. ואין
מך אלא עני, Ve'ein mach ella ani, מך mach means a poor,
to be
weak, שנאמר וימכו מערכך. shene'emar v'yamchu me'erkecha. ואין מקרה, Ve'ein mikreh, how
do we know מקרה mikreh means God, אלא הקדוש ברוך הוא, ella
Hakadosh Baruch Hu, שנאמר המקרה במים עליותיו, shene'emar hamikreh vamayim aliyosav, God
spreads his upper chambers with water. So and again, with water, so
means the rain will be weakened. Now here, besides the idea of
Torah, water, rain, water, and that obvious connection, I think the other
point here is also about this whole thing I was talking about
about the sense of the how the intimacy and God's presence, manifest
presence and connection to us. Our learning of תורה is our way
of being close to God, our way of connecting to דבר ה'.
devar Hashem. Let's also not forget that דבר ה' devar Hashem comes
down from heaven like the rain comes down, יזל כמטר לקחי. yezal
kamatar likchi. So our side of that relationship is our learning of
the תורה. If we weaken our side, then we're also like weakening
God as it were, and we're weakening God's ability to be present
and connect to us in a similar matter, and that way of
God's connecting is expressed through the rain. So there really seems here
to be not just about Torah as water, but about this sense
of this relationship
and this way of manifesting the connection. We do it through תורה.
If we weaken it, then that weakens God's connection to us as
well. רב יוסף אמר מהכא, Rav Yosef amar mehacha, רב יוסף Rav
Yosef says from here we will derive the thing, ועתה לא ראו
אור בהיר הוא בשחקים ורוח עברה ותטהרם, ve'atah lo ra'u or bahir
hu bash'chakim veruach avrah utiharem,
and you did not see the clear light in the heavens and
the wind will pass through and cleanse them. ואין אור אלא תורה,
Ve'ein or ella Torah, the light is Torah, שנאמר כי נר מצוה
ותורה אור. shene'emar ki ner mitzvah v'Torah or. בהיר הוא בשחקים. Bahir
hu bash'chakim. And so therefore, if we were not ראו אור, ra'u
or, so then the wind... passes away and clears the sky of
clouds and clears away the rain if we did not see the
light of תורה. And what's בהיר הוא בשחקים? bahir hu bash'chakim?
It is clear in the heavens. תנא דבי רבי ישמעאל, אפילו בשעה
שרקיע נעשה בהורין בהורין, afillu b'sha'ah sheraki'a na'aseh behorin behorin,
even when the heavens are like little splotches, meaning that it's getting
dark and cloudy, להוריד טל ומטר, lehorid tal umatar, and it looks
like it's going to rain, but if you didn't learn תורה, רוח
עברה ותטהרם, ru'ach avra ut'taharem,
a wind will pass by and cleanse it, but I mean clear
it from clouds so there won't be rain.
Okay, so I guess we'll end here and we'll pick up tomorrow
with other reasons why the rains might be withheld. All right.